<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Cities just vindication, or, A scourge for a vagabond libel intituled, Goodman Country to his worship, the city</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258896</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 176:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Cities just vindication, or, A scourge for a vagabond libel intituled, Goodman Country to his worship, the city</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On the election of sheriffs.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Goodman Country to his worship, the city of London.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Politics and government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57723:1"/>
            <head>THE CITIES Juſt Vindication: OR, A Scourge for a Vagabond LIBEL, INTITULED, <hi>Goodman Country to his Worſhip the City.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Shall not ſpend time in Hunting out the <hi>Abſconded</hi> Author of this Paper, Though by the impertinent Contents <hi>dangling</hi> down its ſides, one might give a ſhrewd <hi>gueſs.</hi> There is a certain Worſhipful <hi>Scribbler</hi> that peſters the Town with a <hi>Litter</hi> of Pamphlets much of the ſame <hi>complexion,</hi> and juſt ſo <hi>accoutred, Buffoon</hi> in the Text, and <hi>Stateſman</hi> in the Margin. But whether it be He, or onely ſome puny <hi>Imitator</hi> of the ſame <hi>Caſt,</hi> is not much material. Our buſineſs is to conſider its <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>ſcope;</hi> which, without Spectacles of <hi>Prejudice,</hi> may be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be <hi>A Libel</hi> upon the City of <hi>London;</hi> and perhaps it is the firſt time that ever that <hi>Honourable Corporation</hi> was ſo openly and effrontedly, and withal ſo cauſeleſly <hi>ſcandall'd:</hi> For can any thing be more falſe and ſlanderous than that—<hi>The City proudly and inſolently calls all the Proteſtants that go to Church, by the name of Church-Papiſts, and Popiſhly affected?</hi> And yet this He no leſs than four times repeats in leſs than forty lines. Again, he takes them all to task — <hi>Come, come, leave your Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Fooling:</hi> As if our Citizens, every Mothers Childe, were turn'd Bedlamites and Jack-Adamſes. Nay, not content to repreſent them as Changlings and Mad men, he makes them Cannibals and Villains too, that will <hi>Treat the beſt and greateſt part of the Nation with Blows and bloody Perſecution.</hi> And immediately after feigns them ready prepared for a <hi>Rebellion, longing after an Holy War, to fight the Lords Battel;</hi> and preſcribes <hi>where</hi> they <hi>ſhall muſter,</hi> and <hi>where</hi> they <hi>muſt not quarter</hi> their <hi>Troops,</hi> &amp;c. Now what can all this tend to, but to create Jealouſies in the mind of the King? (were he not (as we know, and bleſs God he is) a Prince of greater wiſdom than to hearken to the miſchievous ſuggeſtions of any ſuch vile mercenary Incendiaries:) To make him ſuſpect the Loyalty of his Imperial City? and render the Inhabitants thereof infamous, and for ever odious to all the good People and Loyal Subjects in the world?</p>
            <p>But what's the matter? what <hi>horrid Crime</hi> has <hi>London</hi> committed to give cauſe for ſuch <hi>black Reflections?</hi> Nothing in the world, Sirs, but choſen according to Cuſtom a couple of <hi>Sheriffs.</hi> This our Author acknowledges at firſt ſtep, the occaſion of all his out-cries <hi>We have of late been in a woundy Pudder and Tattle about the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Sheriffs.</hi> Here he belies the Country as liberally as afterwards the City; for ſure Country-men are generally more diſcreet than to trouble themſelves ſo much about a matter that did not concern them; eſpecially if they are ſo very indifferent as he preſently tells us, <hi>Not to care what they are, or what they will be, or what Party they are of, as long as they have money.</hi> But though he makes his ſuppoſed Country fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k ſuch ſilly regardleſs fellows, yet he muſt give us who are concern'd, leave to be more circumſpect, and to <hi>chuſe</hi> men (as much as in us lies) that are likely by their <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> to be moſt <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to the Publick: for though we neglect not the <hi>Eſtate,</hi> yet we ſhould not (whatever we <hi>have done</hi>) make <hi>that the ſole Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification.</hi> For why ſhould ſuch <hi>Offices</hi> be intruſted in the hands of any whoſe <hi>Brains</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57723:2"/>lie in their <hi>Cleeſt,</hi> or whoſe Zeal for the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion reaches no further than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning an <hi>Health,</hi> or who ſhall think they have laudably diſcharg'd their <hi>Duty</hi> when they have ſpent a <hi>thouſand pounds</hi> or <hi>two</hi> in making people <hi>drunk</hi> for the <hi>Honour of the City.</hi> We ſpeak not this to <hi>reflect</hi> on any, much leſs the worthy <hi>Gentlemen</hi> late in nomination, (who for ought we hear, were perſons very well qualified, and the onely reaſon why they were <hi>not Elected,</hi> ſeems to be, that they <hi>had too many Friends</hi> in the City who were unwilling to vote them into a Charge ſo <hi>troubleſome</hi> and <hi>expenſive;</hi>) we mention it onely to confute that ſage <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> of our little <hi>Sir Poll,</hi> wherewith he ſtruts his Margin — That <hi>It is no matter who the City chuſes for Sheriffs, ſo they are wealthy.</hi> But before this, he falls into a <hi>Raving fit,</hi> and talks of carrying the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> a <hi>Battel,</hi> and a <hi>Victory,</hi> and this attended with <hi>Houting and Shouting, and flouriſhing of Handkerchiefs.</hi> 'Tis hard to reconcile it to ſenſe, how the City can be ſaid thus to Battel and <hi>Tryumph</hi> over it ſelf; but it ſeems he would have <hi>his folks</hi> in the Country believe that the Livery-men went to <hi>Loggerheads</hi> about their Choice, and a <hi>pitcht field</hi> to have been fought in <hi>Guild-hall.</hi> This is not the <hi>firſt</hi> miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that buſineſs; and though we thought it had been ſufficiently <hi>clear'd,</hi> and the Authors of ſuch Stories cover'd with <hi>guilty Bluſhes;</hi> yet ſince he <hi>revives</hi> it, let us briefly review the matter.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>London</hi> has a Right (though this <hi>Libeller</hi> take liberty to <hi>jeer</hi> at it) practis'd time out of mind, allow'd by many <hi>Charters,</hi> and confirm'd by divers <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> freely to elect every year their Sheriffs. To this purpoſe being met in <hi>Common Hall,</hi> the two Gentlemen, ſince <hi>Declared,</hi> were choſen by <hi>majority</hi> of Hands (in the judgment of moſt indifferent Spectators, near <hi>Ten</hi> to one;) and the preſent Sheriffs gave their Opinion, that they were <hi>Elected.</hi> It happened (I know not <hi>why,</hi> or out of what <hi>deſigne</hi>) ſome perſons preſent would, notwithſtanding the apparent <hi>Diſproportion,</hi> demand a <hi>Poll,</hi> which was as freely granted; but <hi>adjourn'd</hi> (moſt Citizens apprehended contrary to <hi>former Cuſtom)</hi> for deciſion, from time to time for ſeveral days after: ſo that no Surprize, Tumult, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could be pretended. This being admitted and accompliſht, upon ſumming up the Books, it appeared that the firſt two had fairly near a thouſand Names a piece more than the others; and ſo they were declared the <hi>Free Choice</hi> of the City.</p>
            <p>Now where's the <hi>Treaſon</hi> of all this? or if there were any <hi>Faction,</hi> on which ſide did it lie? How does this buſineſs wound the <hi>Church of England,</hi> or concern <hi>Forty one?</hi> or why muſt this <hi>Gaffer Two-ſhoes</hi> poſt up a Letter to the City of <hi>London,</hi> and charge it with <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> upon this occaſion?</p>
            <p>But we muſt dive a little <hi>deeper,</hi> if we would fadome the bottom of theſe peſtilent <hi>Scribblers</hi> Intrigues. 'Tis too apparent there are a ſort of men in the world that would be taken for <hi>good Proteſtants,</hi> and the <hi>moſt Loyal</hi> Subjects, who very induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, though no leſs <hi>ſubtlely,</hi> and under <hi>odd Diſguiſes,</hi> endeavour to <hi>leſſen</hi> or utterly <hi>efface</hi> the belief of the Popiſh Plot, and <hi>baulk</hi> the proſecution of the Conſpirators, and at the ſame time <hi>take all occaſions</hi> (and rather than fail, will <hi>make ſome</hi>) to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and <hi>exaſperate</hi> Proteſtants one againſt another, and create miſunderſtandings, and <hi>horridly</hi> repreſent the moſt innocent Actions, and particularly amuſe people that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is in danger, and the Government ready to be invaded by ſome Proteſtants, and that all <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in point of Ceremony are far more dangerous than <hi>Papiſts;</hi> that Forty one is reviv'd, and a Rebellion carrying on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to take right meaſures of their deſignes herein, we muſt conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That within theſe two years there was diſcovered, juſt when it was ripe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and ready to involve us all in Bloud and Confuſion, <hi>A Damnable Popiſh Plot.</hi> And that the ſame was <hi>real,</hi> we have (after a long Examination) it atteſted by the King in repeated <hi>Proclamations,</hi> by ſeveral Parliaments in <hi>unanimous Votes,</hi> by all the <hi>Judges</hi> of the Land in their proceedings, and by the <hi>Church</hi> in publick <hi>Prayers</hi> and Thankſgivings for our Deliverance. So that whoever ſhall deny or doubt of it, muſt neceſſarily be guilty of the moſt ſawcy impudence, in giving <hi>the lye</hi> to the greateſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities on Earth, and ought juſtly to be eſteemed as an <hi>Accomplice</hi> or Abetter of that horrid Conſpiracy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reality of a Dlot of that <hi>vaſt</hi> undertaking, and ſo <hi>far advanc'd,</hi> being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, can it be ſuppoſed, that <hi>no body</hi> but poor <hi>Ned Coleman</hi> and half a ſcore <hi>raskally Jeſuits</hi> were concern'd in it? 'Tis true, there are ſome people would gladly lay it wholly on the <hi>Society.</hi> The Jeſuits (ſay they) are <hi>Villains,</hi> and <hi>always plotting</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but it cannot be thought that the Body of <hi>Catholicks</hi> could be drawn in to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any ſuch Baſeneſs.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57723:3"/>
            <p>To this we anſwer, This is but an old thred-bare <hi>Shift.</hi> The Gunpowder-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we have oft been told was carried on by a few <hi>Deſperado's,</hi> the buſineſs in <hi>Ireland</hi> (where there were Two hundred thouſand Innocents moſt barbarouſly murder'd) was onely the Heat of a few <hi>zealous Tories,</hi> &amp;c. But in truth, theſe things being of the nature of thoſe, <hi>Quae nunquam laudantur niſi peracta, which are never own'd till accompliſht,</hi> we are to look upon ſuch Pretenſions as frivolous and <hi>deſigning.</hi> Thoſe that now pretend to <hi>abominate</hi> it, would, if it had taken effect, have applauded it as <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>meritorious.</hi> And whereas they would <hi>pin</hi> it onely on the Jeſuits, 'tis well known moſt of the <hi>Popiſh Nobility</hi> and Gentry have perſons of that <hi>Society</hi> for their <hi>Confeſſors.</hi> Now if they are (as theſe little Advocates agree) people of ſuch <hi>deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate principles,</hi> will they not (having ſuch <hi>opportunities) ſoon leaven the whole Lump?</hi> He that acknowledges Jeſuits are <hi>Plotters,</hi> will but in vain deny, that all <hi>the reſt</hi> whoſe <hi>Souls</hi> they have the conduct of (which are the <hi>greateſt part</hi> and of the greateſt influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in <hi>England</hi>) are very <hi>likely</hi> to be ſo too.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Agreeing therefore (as neceſſarily we muſt) That 'tis not likely <hi>a few</hi> ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſuch a deſign, which 'twas impoſſible to carry on without great <hi>numbers</hi> of perſons of <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Eſtates;</hi> and that 'tis probable the <hi>Body</hi> of Papiſts were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally engaged, or fairly diſpoſed to joyn therein; can any <hi>vigilance</hi> be too great, any <hi>care</hi> too much? is not a <hi>charitable union</hi> amongſt Proteſtants neceſſary, and ſtrict <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> but requiſite to obviate and puniſh ſuch a Conſpiracy?</p>
            <p n="4">4. But this Plot having thus taken <hi>wind,</hi> how ſhould the Traitors ſecure their repute, make good their <hi>Retreat,</hi> or gain preſent Impunity, and future opportunities for an <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-game,</hi> but either by an <hi>obſtiante out-facing,</hi> or a <hi>Politick diverſion?</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> they ran as far as 'twould go, witneſs the impudent denyals of the Traitors at the Gibbet, wherein ſeveral of them have notoriouſly been proved <hi>Liars,</hi> as <hi>Gavan, Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> Witneſs too their numerous bare-fac'd Pamphlets, as, <hi>The Compendium, &amp;c.</hi> But finding this too ſhort, they take up the <hi>ſecond:</hi> Then comes on the forging of a <hi>Proteſtant Plot,</hi> (happily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered at Colonel <hi>Manſels</hi> Lodgings) the <hi>Buzze</hi> that the Church of <hi>England</hi> was in danger, and the out-cry of <hi>Forty one,</hi> without the leaſt grounds in the world: but thus Thieves purſued, hope to eſcape by crying <hi>ſtop Thief</hi> after an honeſt man; and crafty <hi>Lapwings</hi> draw people from their own Neſts, by fluttering and <hi>Mewing</hi> at a diſtance. And though it were the moſt unaccountable notion imaginable, That the <hi>Church of England</hi> ſhould ſuffer or be endangered by a vigorous proſecution of <hi>Popiſh Traitors.</hi> yet by the induſtry of the Broachers, this conceit has not a little ſerved their intereſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They have therefore procured, (or at leaſt ſo it has happened) That multitudes of wheadling ſquinting Pamphlets are daily ſpawn'd abroad, ſome to <hi>Ridicule</hi> the Plot, and Aſperſe the <hi>Evidence,</hi> others to Create Jealouſies and Animoſities; ſome to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance Accounts, and repreſent Papiſts and <hi>diſſenting</hi> Proteſtants <hi>equally dangerous.</hi> And though the firſt are actually proved <hi>guilty,</hi> but the ſecond beſides contributing to His Majeſties <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> have ever ſince moſt peacefully demean'd themſelves, yet ſo prevalent are theſe dividing <hi>Charms,</hi> That the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not only ſet at a greater diſtance, and ſo <hi>new Fewds</hi> raiſed, but things almoſt brought to that paſs, that the <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> ſeems <hi>forgot</hi> by Proteſtants; and every one that zealouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to detect it, and bring the prime known <hi>Conſpirators</hi> to Juſtice, is preſently ſtigmatiz'd as a <hi>Phanatick,</hi> a Factious Fellow, an enemy to the Church and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what greater Advantages can the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> hope for?</p>
            <p n="6">6. In order to this, obſerve what <hi>ſlender</hi> opportunities they lay hold on. A little debate happens in <hi>London</hi> about <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> ſtraight the whole City is Arraign'd as ready for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</hi> The City in <hi>Common-hall</hi> humbly deſires its <hi>Loyalty</hi> to be ſignified to the King, to take off baſe miſrepreſentations; proteſts its reſolution to ſtand by him to the utmoſt peril; begs His Majeſty to make uſe of His <hi>Great Council,</hi> as a ſure Expedient to fruſtrate the <hi>wicked Councils of Rome.</hi> And the Citizens aſſembled, ſignifie their joyning in this <hi>humble Petition,</hi> and demonſtrate their zealous affection to His Majeſties Perſon and Government, by unanimous (but not <hi>diſorderly</hi>) Acclamations; and this is here carpt at, as <hi>Tumult</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> and the <hi>Triumphs</hi> of the City for a Victory over the <hi>Church of England!</hi> Can any thing be more unjuſt, or indeed more Seditious! or tend more to amuſe our fellow-Subjects in the <hi>Country</hi> or more <hi>diſhonour</hi> and render us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to Nations <hi>abroad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſtill our Author is ſore offended, that any body ſhould ſay there are any ſuch <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phibious</hi> Creatures amongſt us, as <hi>Church-Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants in Maſquerade;</hi> but is not this a ſhrewd ſign that himſelf is one? <hi>Conſcius ipſe ſibi, &amp;c.</hi> For though <hi>no good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57723:4"/>man,</hi> much leſs the <hi>whole City of London</hi> (as they villainouſly aſſert) ever ſaid or thought, <hi>That all that go to Church</hi> were <hi>ſuch;</hi> for without doubt, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in her Doctrine, and by the Writings of her Learned Members, both <hi>Prelates</hi> and others, hath been, and is the greateſt Bulwark againſt Popery: yet 'tis not impoſſible, that <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> may ſhelter themſelves under her <hi>Mantle,</hi> and in their <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,</hi> or when called before a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> pretend to be her <hi>Sons.</hi> And ſuch <hi>furious ones</hi> commonly they ſeem, (by which mark they may be known) that they are ready like thoſe of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> to be calling for fire on all their Brethren, that cannot keep pace with them in Ceremonies and External Obſervations. The Term <hi>Church-Papiſt</hi> is not <hi>new,</hi> but older much than 41; and if we ſee a Jeſuitical or Atheiſtical <hi>villain,</hi> that merely for ſecular ends, or to create diſturbances, vapours of his being a <hi>Son of the Church,</hi> and yet endeavours to weaken the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> whiffle over a <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> againſt the Life of the King, and divert the proſecution of the <hi>Traiterous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratours, &amp;c.</hi> how then can we more appoſitely expreſs him, than by the Title of a <hi>Proteſtant in Maſquerade?</hi> And though no Proteſtant holds it lawful, yet 'tis no wonder for a <hi>Rank Papiſt</hi> to ſwallow <hi>Oaths,</hi> and joyn in outward Communion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Conſcience;</hi> witneſs their Doctrine of <hi>Diſpenſations, &amp;c.</hi> I ſhall onely give you the Teſtimonies of two <hi>Authors,</hi> one a <hi>Papiſt</hi> when he wrote, the other but late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come over from them; and ſo neither unacquainted with their practifes: the firſt a Secular Prieſt (during their quarrel with the Jeſuits) in a Treatiſe printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. Intituled, <hi>A Dialogue between a Gentleman and a Prieſt,</hi> p. 97. has theſe words: — <hi>The Jeſuits have freely permitted Catholicks to go to Church with Proteſtants, and make no ſin nor ſcruple of it; thus no Law could take hold of them, for who could be known to be a Catholick?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gent. <hi>Did they grant this Liberty to all?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prieſt. <hi>In this ſort they did it. If one were a notorious known Catholick where be came, then they taught it to be unlawful in that place to go to Church, by reaſon of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, and no otherwiſe, but if one were not certainly known to be ſuch a Catholick, he might go without offence; upon condition, that if he heard any Heretical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine preached, which moved him to doubt in any point of Faith, he ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently come to ſome of thoſe Fathers to be reſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, one <hi>John Copley</hi> a Seminary Prieſt, (converted from the Romiſh Church) in a Book called — <hi>Doctrinal and Moral Obſervations,</hi> publiſhed <hi>Anno</hi> 1612. in his Epictle to the Reader, thus expreſſes himſelf, — <hi>I muſt give you farther notice, that there are in this Realm many diſſembling Proteſtants,</hi> [there's a Synonymous term for the Proteſtants in Maſquerade] <hi>who outwardly do all the acts of Religion belonging to this Church of</hi> England, <hi>either to ſtay in their places in the Common-weatlh, or to avoid the Penal Laws; and yet in their hearts are reſolved Believers of the Roman Faith, egregiouſly diſſembling both with God and men, and practiſing moſt notorious equivocation, not ſticking to take <hi>Oaths,</hi> receive <hi>Sacraments,</hi> go to <hi>Church,</hi> and commit many a like act directly againſt their Conſciences and perſwaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee by Catholick Teſtimonies what has been done; and is there not as much reaſon for them to play theſe tricks now as ever? Therefore let the Bliſter riſe on that falſe Tongue that would wheadle us into too good an opinion of Popiſh Innocency.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid open our Authors main deſign, I have not only Anſwered <hi>him,</hi> but <hi>two and twenty</hi> Pamphlets beſides, for they are all of a piece. As for the reſt of his Libel, 'tis <hi>fooling</hi> and <hi>impertinence.</hi> Did the people <hi>in King</hi> Edward's, <hi>or Queen</hi> Maries <hi>days, firſt Model and Compile your Religion?</hi> how then will you ſatisfie the Papiſts when they ask you, <hi>where it was before</hi> Luther? In Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> King <hi>Jameſes,</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's time, people went to their <hi>Pariſh Churches, Ergo,</hi> there is now no <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> nor any body that can make miſchief under an honeſt pretence. But how are you ſure, that if ever an Army of <hi>ſixty thouſand men get into the heart of our Kingdom, they ſhall ſo eaſily Conquer it?</hi> Perhaps you are <hi>North Country,</hi> but I aſſure you I am <hi>Weſt,</hi> and our <hi>Volk</hi> are not of the opinion: for if ever we catch you with your <hi>Threeſchre Thouſands,</hi> be they <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or any other <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I, or Scotiſh Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters either, we will in defence of our <hi>King,</hi> and our Religion, ſend you all to <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> and then how will your <hi>Worſhip</hi> anſwer it, for <hi>Beroguing</hi> and <hi>Bepoxing</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> at this fate? We will not <hi>vilifie</hi> any honeſt Church of <hi>England men,</hi> but <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> them; yet we will implore God and the King, that Popiſh and all other Treaſons, may be fully detected and <hi>puniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus withing you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eep your ſelf <hi>cloſe,</hi> and prevent (if you can) <hi>a ſmarter Anſwer</hi> ſhortly from the <hi>Pillory,</hi> or the <hi>Whipping poſt</hi> I commit you to your deſtiny,</p>
            <trailer>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
